The 44 Club collection 1939-2000 CPAA 86-32
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
The 44 Club collection
1939-2000
The 44 Club
CPAA 86-32
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
The 44 Club, a social organization for Polish American professionals with university degrees, was established in November 1939. The Club fostered and promoted interest in Polish language, culture, and intellectual advancement among Polish Americans. The main activities of the club were monthly social gatherings at the houses of members and social fundraisers for scholarships for youths of Polish origin. The collection features materials related to the history of the club. This includes constitutions, by laws, minutes, financial data and information about social events. It covers the years from 1939 untill 2000.
Historical Note
The 44 Club was established on November 19, 1939 as a social organization for Polish Americans with university degrees from the city of New Britain. The all male organizers were indeed professionals with degrees from various universities and they were second generation Polish Americans. Among its members were attorneys, doctors, and bankers. According to the Article I of the club's constitution, the main purpose was to: "aid and foster social and intellectual advancement among Polish-American university men; to encourage education and cultivate and promote greater interest in the language and culture of the Polish race." The name of the organization, Club 44 was suggested by Bill Gryboski because of its patriotic importance. The name goes back to the poem “Forefather's Eve”, by Adam Mickiewicz, a Polish national poet, where he refers to Poland's oppression by the Russians and to the vision of Poland being liberated by an unknown youth whose name is forty four.
The main activities of the club were charitable, educational and social. Club members collected books for local institutions, awarded scholarships and even established the Pine Cone Committee for the sole purpose of awarding scholarships. Club members declined any political involvement or affiliations and concentrated solely on its social aspect.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of minutes, correspondence, social announcements, scholarship information, photographs and history of the Club. The collection also includes memorabilia from the Polish Open Invitational Golf Tournament, one of the club's fundraising activities, donated by Alex M. Rudewicz. Material in the collection covers the years from 1939 untill 2001 although the club continues its activities till today.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas in 1986. Material dated after 1986 was donated in several parts also by Profesor S. A. Blejwas. Memorabilia related to the Polish Open Golf Tournament were donated by Alexander M. Rudewicz in 1999.
Search Terms
Blejwas, Stanislaus A.; Gwiazda, Henry.; The 44 Club; The 44 Club (New Britain, Connecticut).; Polish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Societies, etc. -- History -- 20th Century.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Minutes.; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Programs.; Clippings.; Photographs.
Related Material
For related material from Connecticut Polish American Archives see the following collections: Stanislaus A. Blejwas Collection CPAA 86-14 (box 29, folders 61-63 and box 32, folder 52) Henry Gwiazda Papers CPAA 87-05 (box 2 folders 11-12)
Arrangement
The Material in the collection was arranged chronologically by Prof. S.A. Blejwas who wrote the history of the 44 club for its 50th anniversary. The original arrangement was kept within the collection. Duplicate copies were removed.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Constitutions, by-laws, amendments, 1939-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Constitution adapted November 9, 1939, second constitution adapted November 1947, with annotations. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The 44 Club - photograph of club members (Gryboski, Lexton, Gwiazda) presenting books to the orphanage; negatives from early events and social gatherings., 1940's (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The 44 Club Scholarship Committee - correspondence and list of recipients., 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "A history of 44 Club, 1939 through 1954" by Roman J. Lexton; includes photographs, constitution, amendments and by-laws. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 44 Club clippings and obituaries., 1939-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 44 Club - Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas' records of the club., 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "The 44 Club, 1939-1989, celebrating fifty years of fraternal association" history of the Club by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- " 44 Club - Survey general letter sent to members and summary of responses., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 44 Club - responses to the survey., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The 44 Club": second generation Polonia, by S.A. Blejwas., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 44 Club - research material for history of the club and notes compiled by Prof. Blejwas., 1939-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "44 Club - The history of the Pine Cone Committee: a supplement to the historical record of the Forty Four Club" by Walter Liss and Walter Lachowicz., 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 44 Club - obituaries of deceased club members., 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 44 Club - Treasurer's Book., 1940-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 44 Club - minutes., 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 44 Club - minutes, related correspondence., 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 44 Club history - binder includes first constitution, amendments, list of members, activities and committees., 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Memorabilia from the Polish Open Invitational Golf Tournament. It includes special glasses from 14th Open, 1988 till 20th Open, 1994; golf balls from 1990-1991, 1993-1996, 1998; a towel and pegs. (Box 3, Folder 1)